<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Encænia the Feast of Dedication, celebrated at Lincolnes Inne, in a sermon there vpon Ascension day, 1623 : at the dedication of a new chappell there, consecrated by the Right Reuerend Father in God, the Bishop of London / preached by Iohn Donne ...</title>
            <author>Donne, John, 1572-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7039</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1700</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21498332</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21498332</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24646</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20638)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24646)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1708:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Encænia the Feast of Dedication, celebrated at Lincolnes Inne, in a sermon there vpon Ascension day, 1623 : at the dedication of a new chappell there, consecrated by the Right Reuerend Father in God, the Bishop of London / preached by Iohn Donne ...</title>
                  <author>Donne, John, 1572-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 41 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Avg. Mat. for Thomas Iones, and are to bee sold at his shop in the Strand, at the Blacke Rauen, neere vnto Saint Clements Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A4) B-F⁴ G¹.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John X, 22 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Church dedication sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:24646:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24646:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Encaenia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE FEAST OF DEDICATION.</p>
            <p>CELEBRATED AT LINCOLNES INNE, in a Sermon there vpon Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>day,</hi> 1623.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At the Dedication of a new Chappell</hi> there, Conſecrated by the Right Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, the Biſhop of LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preached by</hi> IOHN DONNE, Deane of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. PAVLS.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by AVG. MAT. for THOMAS IONES, and are to bee ſold at his Shop in the Strand, at the blacke <hi>Rauen,</hi> neere vnto Saint <hi>Clements</hi> Church. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:24646:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24646:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MASTERS OF THE BENCH, AND the reſt of the Honourable Societie of LINCOLNES INNE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pleaſed you to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe your intereſt in me, and to expreſſe your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to mee, in inuiting mee to preach this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: and it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you to doe both ouer againe, in inuiting me to publiſh it. To this latter ſeruice I was the more inclinable, becauſe, though in it I had no occaſion to handle any matter of Controuerſie betweene vs, and thoſe of the <hi>Romane Perſwaſion,</hi> yet the whole body and frame of the <hi>Sermon,</hi> is oppoſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one peſtilent calumny of theirs, that
<pb facs="tcp:24646:3"/>
wee haue cast off all diſtinction of places, and of dayes, and all outward meanes of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the deuotion of the Congregation. For this vſe, I am not ſorry that it is made publique, for I ſhall neuer bee ſorry to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare plainly, and openly, and directly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſguiſe or modification, in the vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our <hi>Church</hi> from the imputations and calumnies of that Aduerſary. If it had no publique vſe, yet I ſhould ſatisfie my ſelfe in this, that it is done in obedience to that, which you may call your Request, but I ſhall call your Commandement vpon</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant in Chriſt Ieſus. IOHN DONNE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:24646:3"/>
            <head>The Prayer before the <hi>Sermon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall, and moſt gracious <hi>God,</hi> Father of our Lord <hi>Ieſus Christ;</hi> and in him, of all thoſe that are his, As thou diddeſt make him ſo much ours, as that he became like vs, in all things, ſinne onely excepted, make vs ſo much his, as that we may be like him, euen without the exception of ſinne, that all our ſinnes may bee buryed in his wounds, and drowned in his Blood. And as this day wee celebrate his <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> to thee, bee pleaſed to accept our endeauour of confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming our ſelues to his patterne, in rayſing this place for our <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> to him. Leane vpon theſe <hi>Pinnacles,</hi> O Lord, as thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſt vpon <hi>Iacobs Ladder,</hi> and hearken after vs. Bee this thine <hi>Arke,</hi> and let thy <hi>Doue,</hi> thy bleſſed <hi>Spirit,</hi> come in and out, at theſe Windowes: and let a full pot of thy <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> a good meaſure of thy Word, and an
<pb facs="tcp:24646:4"/>
effectuall preaching thereof, bee euermore preſerued, and euermore bee diſtributed in this place. Let the Leproſie of <hi>Superſtition</hi> neuer enter within theſe Walles, nor the hand of <hi>Sacriledge</hi> euer fall vpon them. And in theſe walles, to them that loue <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit</hi> and <hi>Gaine,</hi> manifeſt thou thy ſelfe as a <hi>Treaſure,</hi> and fill them ſo; To them that loue <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> manifeſt thy ſelfe, as <hi>Marrow</hi> and <hi>Fatneſſe,</hi> and fill them ſo; And to them that loue <hi>Preferment,</hi> manifeſt thy ſelfe, as a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and fill them ſo; that ſo thou mayeſt bee all vnto all; giue thy ſelfe wholly to vs all, and make vs all wholly thine. Accept our humble thanks for all, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:24646:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOHN 10.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And it was at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the Feaſt of the Dedication; and it was Winter; and <hi>Ieſus</hi> walked in the Temple in <hi>Salomons</hi> Porch.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint Baſill</hi> in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vpon the 114. <hi>Pſalme;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſill.</note> vpon the like occaſion as drawes vs together now, The conſecration of a Church, makes this the reaſon and the excuſe of his late comming thither to doe that Seruice, that he ſtayd by the way, to conſecrate another Church: I hope euery perſon heere hath done ſo; conſecrated himſelfe, who is a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:24646:5"/>
               <hi>Temple</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> before hee came to aſſiſt, or to teſtifie the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of this place of the Seruice of <hi>God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. Ser. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Noſtra feſtiuitas haec est, quia de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia noſtra;</hi> ſayes <hi>Saint Bernard.</hi> This Feſtiuall belongs to vs, becauſe it is the conſecration of that place, which is ours, <hi>Magis autem noſtra, quia de nobis ipſis:</hi> But it is more properly our Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall, becauſe it is the conſecration of our ſelues to <hi>Gods</hi> ſeruice. For, <hi>Sanctae Animae propter inhabitantem Spiritum;</hi> your <hi>Soules</hi> are holy, by the inhabita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Gods</hi> holy ſpirit, who dwells in them. <hi>Sancta corpora propter inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantem animam;</hi> Your <hi>Bodies</hi> are holy, by the inhabitation of thoſe ſanctified <hi>Soules. Sancti parietes, propter Corpora Sanctorum.</hi> Theſe walles are holy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>God</hi> meet here with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe walls to glorifie him. But yet theſe places are not onely conſecrated &amp; ſanctified by your comming; but to bee ſanctified alſo for your comming;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:24646:5"/>
that ſo, as the Congregation ſanctifies the place, the place may ſanctifie the Congregation too. They muſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany one another; holy perſons and holy places; If men would waſh ſheep in the <hi>Baptiſterie,</hi> in the <hi>Font,</hi> thoſe ſheep were not chriſtned. If prophane men, or idolatrous men, pray here after their way, their prayers are not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the place. Neither if it be after polluted, doth the place retain that ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie, which is this day to be deriued vpon it, and to bee imprinted in it.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Text</hi> ſettles vs vpon both theſe conſiderations, The holy place,<note place="margin">Diuiſie.</note> and the holy perſon. It was the <hi>Feaſt of the Dedication:</hi> there's the holineſſe of the place; And the holy perſon, was holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it ſelfe in the perſon of <hi>Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> who <hi>walked in the Temple in Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Porch.</hi> Theſe two will bee our two parts: And the firſt of theſe wee ſhall make vp of theſe pieces. Firſt, we ſhall ſee a lawfull vſe of <hi>Feaſts,</hi> of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiuall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:24646:6"/>
dayes.</hi> And then of other <hi>Feaſts,</hi> then were inſtituted by <hi>God himſelfe;</hi> diuers were ſo; this was not. And thirdly, not only a <hi>feſtiuall</hi> ſolemnizing of ſome one thing, at ſome one time, for the preſent, but an <hi>Anniuerſary</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to that ſolemnitie euery yeare; And laſtly, in that firſt part, this <hi>Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall</hi> in particular, The Feaſt of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication</hi> of the <hi>Temple:</hi> that ſanctified the place, that ſhall determine that part. In the ſecond part, <hi>The holineſſe of the perſon,</hi> we ſhall carry your thoughts no farther, but vpon this, That euen this holy perſon <hi>Ieſus</hi> himſelfe, would haue recourſe to this place, thus dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, thus ſanctified: And vpon this, that hee would doe that eſpecially at ſuch times, as hee might countenance and authoriſe the Ordinances and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Church, which had appointed this <hi>Feſtiuall.</hi> And this, ſayes the <hi>Text,</hi> he did in the <hi>Winter:</hi> Firſt, <hi>Et ſi Hiems,</hi> though it were Winter, hee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:24646:6"/>
came, and walked in the <hi>Porch,</hi> a little inconuenience kept him not off: And, <hi>Quia Hiems,</hi> becauſe it was Winter, he walked in the <hi>Porch</hi> which was coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not in the Temple which was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen. So that heere with modeſtie, and without ſcandall he condemned not the fauouring of a mans health, euen in the <hi>Temple, And it was at Ieruſalem, the Feaſt of the Dedication; and it was Winter; and Ieſus walked in the Temple in Salomons Porch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In our firſt part, <hi>Holy places,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Part. Feſta.</note> wee looke firſt vpon the times of our mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting there, <hi>Holy dayes.</hi> The root of all thoſe is the <hi>Sabboth,</hi> that God planted himſelfe, euen in himſelfe, in his owne reſt, from the Creation. But the root, and thoſe branches which grow from that root, are of the ſame nature, and the ſame name: And therefore as well of the flower, as of the root of a Roſe, or of a Violet, we would ſay, This is a Violet, this is a Roſe: ſo as well to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:24646:7"/>
Feaſts of <hi>Gods</hi> inſtitution, as to the firſt <hi>Sabboth, God</hi> giues that name; hee cals thoſe ſeuerall Feaſts which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, <hi>Sabboths;</hi> enioynes the ſame things to be done vpon them, inflicts the ſame puniſhments vpon them that breake them.<note place="margin">Leuit. 23.</note> So that there is one <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie,</hi> that is the ſoule of all <hi>Sabboths,</hi> of all <hi>Feſtiualls;</hi> howſoeuer all <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths</hi> haue a ceremoniall part in them, yet there is a <hi>Morall</hi> part that inani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates them all; they are elemented of <hi>Ceremonie,</hi> but they animated with <hi>Moralitie.</hi> And that <hi>Moralitie</hi> is in them all, <hi>Reſt:</hi> for if <hi>Adam</hi> could name crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures according to their nature, <hi>God</hi> could name his <hi>Sabboth</hi> according to the nature of it, and <hi>Sabboth</hi> is <hi>Reſt.</hi> It is a <hi>Reſt</hi> of two kindes; our reſt, and <hi>Gods</hi> reſt. Our reſt is the ceſſation from labour on thoſe dayes; <hi>Gods</hi> reſt, is our ſanctifying of the day: for ſo in the religious ſacrifice of <hi>Noah,</hi> when hee was come out of the <hi>Arke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> is ſaid
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:24646:7"/>
to haue ſmelt, <hi>Odorem quietis,</hi> the ſauour of reſt: vpon thoſe dayes we reſt from ſeruing the world, and <hi>God</hi> reſts in our ſeruing of him. And as <hi>God</hi> takes a tenth part of our goods, in <hi>Tythes,</hi> but yet he takes more too, he takes <hi>Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> ſo though he take a ſeuenth part of our time in the <hi>Sabboth,</hi> yet he takes more too, he appoints other <hi>Sabboths,</hi> other <hi>Feſtiualls,</hi> that he may haue more glory, and we more Reſt: for all wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thoſe two concurre, are <hi>Sabboths. Vacate &amp; videte quoniam ego ſum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ſayes <hi>God.</hi> Firſt <hi>vacate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 46.10</note> reſt from your bodily labours, diſtinguiſh the day, and then <hi>videte,</hi> come hither into the <hi>Lords</hi> preſence, and worſhip the <hi>Lord</hi> your <hi>God,</hi> ſanctifie the day: And in all the <hi>Sabboths</hi> there is ſtill a <hi>Ceſſate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 23.</note> and a <hi>Humiliate animas,</hi> bodily reſt, and ſpirituall ſanctifying of the day. <hi>Holy dayes</hi> then, that is, dayes ſepoſed for <hi>holy vſes,</hi> and for the outward &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſeruice of <hi>God,</hi> are in <hi>Nature,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:24646:8"/>
in that <hi>Morall Law</hi> which is written in the heart of man. That ſuch dayes there muſt be is <hi>Morall;</hi> and this is <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> too, that all things in the ſeruice of God bee done in order; and this alſo, that obedience be giuen to Superiours, in thoſe things wherein they are Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors. And therfore it was to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> as well <hi>Morall,</hi> to obſerue the certaine dayes which <hi>God</hi> had determined, as to obſerue any at all. Not that Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement limitting the dayes, infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a <hi>Moralitie</hi> into thoſe particular dayes: for <hi>Moralitie</hi> is perpetuall; and if that had been <hi>Morall,</hi> it muſt haue been ſo before, and it muſt bee ſo ſtill; <hi>Gods</hi> determining the dayes did not infuſe, not induce a <hi>Moralitie</hi> there, but it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened a former <hi>Moralitie,</hi> that is, an obedience to the commandement, for that time, which <hi>God</hi> had appoynted that for them; for this <hi>Obedience,</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> is perpetuall, and ſo, <hi>Morall.</hi> We depart therfore from that error, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:24646:8"/>
thoſe ancient <hi>Heretiques,</hi> the <hi>Ebionites</hi> begun, and ſome laboured to refreſh in <hi>Saint Gregories</hi> time, and which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues in practiſe in ſome places of the world ſtill; To obſerue both the <hi>Iewes Sabbath,</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtians, Satterday,</hi> and <hi>Sunday</hi> too; becauſe the <hi>Sabboth</hi> is called <hi>Pactum ſempiternum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 31.</note> for to that any of <hi>Saint Auguſtines</hi> Anſweres will ſerue; either that it is called euerlaſting, becauſe it ſignified an euerlaſting reſt; (where be pleaſed to note by the way, that <hi>Holy dayes, Sabbaths,</hi> are not onely inſtituted for <hi>Order,</hi> but they haue their <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and their <hi>Signification;</hi> for <hi>Holy dayes,</hi> (as the Text calls them there) and <hi>New Moones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.16.</note> and the <hi>Sabboth,</hi> were but ſhadowes of things to come:) or elſe the <hi>Sabboth</hi> was called euerlaſting to them, becauſe it bound them euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly, and they might neuer inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it, as ſome other ceremonies they might. But their <hi>Sabboths</hi> bind not vs; we depart from them who thinke ſo;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:24646:9"/>
and ſo we doe from them, who think we are bound to no <hi>Feſtiualls</hi> at all, or at leaſt to none but the <hi>Sabboth.</hi> For <hi>God</hi> requires as much ſeruice from vs, as from the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and to them hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged his <hi>Sabboths,</hi> and made them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. But thoſe were of <hi>Gods</hi> immediat inſtitution: but all that the <hi>Iewes</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued were not ſo; and thats our next conſideration, <hi>Feſtiualls</hi> inſtituted by the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sine Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dato.</note>At firſt, when <hi>God</hi> was alone, it is but <hi>Faciamus,</hi> let <hi>vs, vs</hi> the <hi>Trinity</hi> make man. This was, when <hi>God</hi> was, as we may ſay, <hi>in Coelibatu.</hi> But after <hi>God</hi> hath taken his <hi>ſpouſe,</hi> maried the <hi>Church,</hi> then it is <hi>Cadite nobis vulpes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.15</note> doe <hi>you</hi> take the little Foxes, <hi>you</hi> the <hi>Church;</hi> for <hi>our</hi> vines haue grapes; the vines are <hi>ours; yours</hi> and <hi>mine</hi> ſayes <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the <hi>Church:</hi> and therfore do you looke to them, as well as I. The Tables of the law <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe writ, and gaue them written to <hi>Moſes:</hi> he left none of that to him; not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:24646:9"/>
a power to make other Lawes like thoſe lawes: but for the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> which concern'd the <hi>outward</hi> worſhip of <hi>God,</hi> that was to be made by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod</note> 
               <hi>Iuxta ſimilitudinem,</hi> according to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne which <hi>God</hi> had ſhewed him. <hi>God</hi> hath giuen the <hi>Church</hi> a paterne of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dayes,</hi> in thoſe <hi>Sabboths</hi> which hee himſelfe inſtituted, and according to the paterne, the <hi>Church</hi> hath inſtituted more: and <hi>Recte feſta Eccleſiae colunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>qui ſe Eccleſiae filios recognoſcunt:</hi> They who diſdaine not the name of <hi>ſonnes</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> refuſe not to celebrate the daies which are of the <hi>Churches</hi> inſtitution. There was no immediate commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>God</hi> for that <hi>Holy day,</hi> which <hi>Mordechai,</hi> by his letters eſtabliſh'd;<note place="margin">Eſter 9.23</note> but yet the <hi>Iewes</hi> vndertooke to do as <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dechai</hi> had written to them. There was no ſuch commandement for this <hi>Holy day,</hi> in the Text; and yet that was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, as long as they had any beeing. And where the reaſon remaines, the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:24646:10"/>
practiſe may; The <hi>Iewes</hi> did, we may inſtitute new <hi>Holy dayes.</hi> And not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſitory daies, for a preſent thanks giuing for a preſent benefit, but <hi>Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries,</hi> perpetuall memorials of <hi>Gods</hi> deliuerances. And thats our next ſtep.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaria.</note>Both the <hi>Holy dayes,</hi> which we na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before, which were inſtituted with out ſpeciall Commaundement from <hi>God,</hi> were ſo. That of <hi>Mordechai,</hi> he commanded to be kept euery yeare for two dayes, and this in the Text, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Maccabeus</hi> commanded to be kept yearely for eight dayes, which was more then was appoynted to any of the <hi>Holy dayes,</hi> inſtituted by <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for the Feſtiuall alone. According to which paterne,<note place="margin">Felix.</note> one <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> ordained that the Feſtiuals of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of <hi>Churches</hi> ſhould bee yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly celebrated in thoſe places;<note place="margin">Greg.</note> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other extended the Feſtiuall to eight dayes; at leaſt at the firſt dedication thereof, if not euery yeare: that <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:24646:10"/>
might not onely be put into the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the place, but ſetled in it. <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Moſes</hi> made the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> a <hi>Song,</hi> becauſe, as hee ſayes,<note place="margin">Deut. 31.19</note> howſoeuer they did by the Law, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forget that <hi>Song,</hi> &amp; that <hi>Song</hi> ſhould be his witneſſe againſt them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would <hi>God</hi> haue vs inſtitute ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne memorialls of his great deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, that if when thoſe dayes come about, we doe not glorifie him, that might aggrauate our condemnation. Euery fift of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> riſes vp, to hearken whether we meet to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him, for his great deliuerance of his <hi>Maieſty,</hi> before he bleſt vs with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in this Kingdome: and when he finds vs zealous in our thankes for that, he giues vs farther bleſsings. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he is vp as early euery fift of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember,</hi> to hearken if we meet to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him for that deliuerance ſtill; and if hee ſhould finde our zeale leſſe then heretofore, hee would wonder why.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:24646:11"/>
               <hi>Gods</hi> principall, his radicall <hi>Holy day,</hi> the <hi>Sabboth,</hi> had a weekly returne; his other <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> inſtituted by himſelfe, and thoſe which were inſtituted by thoſe paternes, that of <hi>Mordechai,</hi> that of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> &amp; thoſe of the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church,</hi> They all return once a yeare. <hi>God</hi> would keepe his Courts once a yeare, and ſee whether wee make our apparances as heeretofore; that if not, hee may know it. Feaſtes in generall, Feaſtes inſtituted by the <hi>Church</hi> alone, Feaſts in their yearely returne and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, haue their vſe, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly thoſe Feaſts of the Dedication of <hi>Churches,</hi> which was properly and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally the Feaſt of this <hi>Text. It was the Feaſt of Dedication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Encaeuia.</note>As it diminiſhes not, preiudices not <hi>Gods Eternitie,</hi> that wee giue him his <hi>Quando,</hi> certaine times of Inuocation, <hi>God</hi> is not the leſſe <hi>yeſterday,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Temple.</note> 
               <hi>and to day, and the ſame for euer,</hi> becauſe wee meet here to day, and not yeſterday, ſo it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:24646:11"/>
not, preiudices not <hi>Gods Vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie</hi> and <hi>Omnipreſence,</hi> that wee giue him his <hi>Vbi,</hi> certaine places for Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Thats not the leſſe true, that <hi>the moſt High dwells not in Temples made with handes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 7.48.</note> though <hi>God</hi> accept at our hands our dedication of certaine pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to his ſeruice, &amp; manifeſt his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king more effectually, more energeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally in thoſe places, then in any other. for when we pray, <hi>Our Father which art in Heauen,</hi> It is not (ſayes <hi>Saint Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi>) that wee deny him to bee heere,<note place="margin">Chryſoſtome.</note> where wee kneele when we ſay that Prayer, but it is that we acknowledge him to be there, where he can graunt, and accompliſh our prayer. It is as <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> hath very well expreſſed it,<note place="margin">Origen.</note> 
               <hi>Vt in melioribus mundi requiramus Deum:</hi> That ſtill wee looke for <hi>God</hi> in the beſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; looke for him, as he heares our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, here, in the beſt places of this world, in his Houſe, in the Church; looke for him as he graunts our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:24646:12"/>
in the beſt place of the next world, at the right hand, and in the boſome of the <hi>Father.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 30.13</note> When <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayes that <hi>the word of</hi> God <hi>is not beyond Sea,</hi> he addes, <hi>It is not ſo beyond Sea, as that thou muſt not haue it without ſending thither.</hi> When he ſayes there, <hi>it is not in heauen,</hi> he adds, <hi>not ſo in heauen, as that one must goe vp, before hee can haue it.</hi> The word of <hi>God,</hi> is beyond Sea, the true word, truly preached in many true <hi>Churches</hi> there, but yet we haue it here, within theſe Seas too; <hi>God</hi> is in Heauen, but yet hee is here, within theſe walles too. And therefore the impietie of the <hi>Maniche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> exceeded all the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the <hi>God</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> to be an impotent, an vnperfect <hi>God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee commaunded <hi>Moſes</hi> firſt to make him a <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and then <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to make him a <hi>Temple,</hi> as though he needed a Houſe. <hi>God</hi> does not need a houſe, but man does need, that <hi>God</hi> ſhould haue a Houſe. And therefore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:24646:12"/>
the firſt queſtion, that <hi>Chriſts</hi> firſt <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> asked of him, was <hi>Magiſter, vbi habitas,</hi> they would know his ſtanding houſe, where he hath promiſed to bee alwaies within, and where at the ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Bell, ſome body comes to anſwere you, to take your errand, to offer your Prayers to <hi>God,</hi> to returne his pleaſure in the preaching of his Word to you. The many and heauy Lawes, with which ſacred and ſecular ſtories abound, againſt the prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of places, appropriated to <hi>Gods</hi> ſeruice, and that religious cuſtome, that paſſed almoſt through all ciuill Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that an oath, which was the bond between man, and man, had the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Obligation, if that were taken in the <hi>Church,</hi> in the preſence of <hi>God,</hi> (for ſuch was the practiſe of <hi>Rome</hi> towards her enemies, <hi>Tango aras medioſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ignes,</hi> to make their vowes of hoſtility in the <hi>Church,</hi> and at time of diuine Seruice, (and ſuch is their practiſe ſtill, they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:24646:13"/>
ſeale their Treaſons in the <hi>Sacrament</hi>) ſuch was <hi>Romes</hi> practiſe towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſuch was the practiſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers towards <hi>Rome,</hi> (for ſo <hi>Anniball</hi> ſayes, that his father <hi>Amilcar</hi> ſwore him at the <hi>Altar,</hi> that he ſhould neuer bee reconciled to <hi>Rome,</hi> (And ſuch is your practiſe ſtill, as often as you meet here, you renew your band to <hi>God,</hi> that you will neuer bee reconciled to the Superſtitions of <hi>Rome</hi>) all theſe, and all ſuch as theſe, and ſuch as theſe are infinite, heap vp teſtimonies, that euen in <hi>Nature</hi> there is a diſpoſition to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and appropriate certaine places to <hi>Gods</hi> ſeruice. And this impreſſion in nature is illuſtrated in the Law, as the time, ſo the place is diſtinguiſhed, <hi>Yee ſhall keepe my Sabboths,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leui. 19.30</note> there is the <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>you ſhall reuerence my Sanctuary,</hi> there is the place. But that they may be reuerenced, that they may bee San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuaries, they are to be ſanctified; and thats the <hi>Encaenia,</hi> the Dedication.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:24646:13"/>Euen in thoſe things which accrue vnto <hi>God,</hi> and become his,<note place="margin">Encaenia.</note> by another title, then as he is Lord of all, by <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that is, by appropriation, by dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to his vſe and Seruice, There is a <hi>Lay Dedication,</hi> and an <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Dedication.</hi> I hope the diſtinction of <hi>Laytie,</hi> and <hi>Clergie,</hi> the words, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize no man. <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi> too might haue iuſt cauſe to decline the words, as they did; when ſo much was ouer-attributed to that <hi>Clergie</hi> which they intend, as that they were ſo <hi>Sors Domini,</hi> the <hi>Lords portion,</hi> as that the world had no portion in them, and yet they had the greateſt portion of the world; and howe little ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they had to doe with <hi>God,</hi> yet no <hi>State,</hi> no <hi>King</hi> might haue any thing to doe with them. But, as long as we declare, that by the <hi>Layetie</hi> we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the people glorifying <hi>God</hi> in their ſecular callings, and by the <hi>Clergie,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſepoſed by his ordinance, for ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:24646:14"/>
functions, The <hi>Layetie</hi> no farther remoou'd then the <hi>Clergie,</hi> The <hi>Clergie</hi> no farther entitled then the <hi>Layetie,</hi> in the blood of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> neither in the effuſion of that blood vpon the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> nor in the participation of that blood in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and that an equall care in <hi>Clergie,</hi> and <hi>Layetie,</hi> of doing the duties of their ſeuerall callings, giues them an equall intereſt in the ioyes, and glory of heauen, I hope no man is ſcandaliz'd with the names. The <hi>Lay Dedication</hi> then is, the voluntary ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendring of this piece of ground thus built, to <hi>God.</hi> For we muſt ſay, as <hi>Saint Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ananias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>Whiles it remain'd, was that not your owne?</hi> and now, when that is raiſed (ſauing that there was <hi>Dedicatio Intentionalis,</hi> a purpoſe from the beginning to appropriate it, to this holy vſe) might you not, till this houre, haue made this roome your Hall, if you would? But this is your Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that you haue cheerfully purſued
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:24646:14"/>
your firſt holy purpoſes, and deliuer now into the hands of this ſeruant of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Right Reuerend Father the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of this See,</hi> a place to be preſented to <hi>God</hi> for you, by him, not misbecom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of the great <hi>God,</hi> who is pleaſed to dwell thus amongſt vs. What was ſpent in <hi>Salomons Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> is not told vs. What was prepared, before it was begun, is ſuch a ſumme, as certainly, if all the <hi>Chriſtian Kings</hi> that are, would ſend in all that they haue, at once, to any one ſeruice, all would not equall that ſumme. They gaue there, till they who had the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing therof, complain'd of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and proclaim'd an abſtinence. Yet there was one, who gaue more then all they; for <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayes the poore widdow gaue more then all the reſt, becauſe ſhe gaue all ſhe had. There is a way of giuing more then ſhe gaue; &amp; I, who by your fauours was no ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to the beginning of this work, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:24646:15"/>
an often refreſher of it to your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, and a poore aſsiſtant in laying the firſt ſtone, the materiall ſtone, as I am now, a poore aſsiſtant again in this laying of this firſt formall Stone, the Word &amp; Sacrament, and ſhall euer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be ſo in the ſeruice of this place, I, I ſay, can truly teſtifie, that you (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the whole Societie together of the publike ſtock, the publike treaſury, the publike reuenue) you gaue more then the widow, who gaue all, for you gaue more then all. <hi>A ſtranger ſhall not entermeddle with our ioy,</hi> as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaies: ſtrangers ſhall not know, how ill we were prouided for ſuch a work, when we begun it, nor with what difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we haue wraſtled in the way; but ſtrangers ſhall know to <hi>Gods</hi> glory, that you haue perfected a work of full three times as much charge, as you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for it at beginning: ſo bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully doth <hi>God</hi> bleſſe, and proſper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions to his glory, with enlarging
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:24646:15"/>
your hearts within, and opening the hearts of others, abroad. And this is <hi>your Dedication,</hi> and that which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preiudice, and for diſtinction, wee call a <hi>Lay Dedication,</hi> though from reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious hearts, and hands.</p>
            <p>There is another <hi>Dedication;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtica</note> that we haue call'd <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> appointed by <hi>God,</hi> ſo as <hi>God</hi> ſpeaks in the ordinances, and in the practiſe of his <hi>Church.</hi> Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Kings are begotten &amp; conceiu'd the naturall way; but that body which is ſo begotten of the blood of Kings, is not a King, no nor a man, till there bee a Soule infuſed by <hi>God.</hi> Here is a <hi>Houſe,</hi> a <hi>Child</hi> conceiu'd (wee may ſay borne) of <hi>Chriſtian parents,</hi> of perſons religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſpoſed to <hi>Gods</hi> glory; but yet, that was to receiue another influence, an inanimation, a quickening, by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conſecration. <hi>Oportet denuo naſci,</hi> holds euen in the children of <hi>Chriſtian parents;</hi> when they are borne, they muſt be borne again by <hi>Baptiſme:</hi> when this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:24646:16"/>
place is thus giuen by you, for <hi>God, opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet denuo dari,</hi> it muſt be giuen againe to <hi>God,</hi> by him, who receiues it of you. It muſt; there ſeems a neceſsitie to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, becauſe euen in <hi>Nature,</hi> there was a conſecration of holy places; <hi>Iacob</hi> in his iourney,<note place="margin">Gen. 28.20.</note> before the <hi>Law,</hi> conſecrated euen that ſtone, which he ſet vp, in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to build <hi>God</hi> a Houſe there. In the time of the <hi>Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 7.1.</note> this Feaſt of Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, was in practiſe; firſt in the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle;</hi> that and all that appertain'd to it, was annointed, and ſanctified: So was <hi>Salomons Temple</hi> after; ſo was that which was reedified after their return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſo was this in the <hi>Text,</hi> after the Heathen had defiled and profan'd the <hi>Altar</hi> thereof, and a new one was erected by <hi>Iudas Maccabeus.</hi> Thus in <hi>Nature,</hi> thus in <hi>Law,</hi> and thus far thus in the <hi>Gospell</hi> too: that as ſure as wee are that the people of <hi>God</hi> had <hi>materiall Churches</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> firſt times, ſo ſure we are, that thoſe places
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:24646:16"/>
had a Sanctitie in them. If that place of <hi>Saint Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.22</note> 
               <hi>Despiſe yee the Church of God?</hi> be to be vnderſtood of the locall, of the materiall <hi>Church,</hi> and not of the <hi>Congregation,</hi> you ſee there is a rebuke for the prophanation of the place, and conſequently a ſanctity in the place. But aſſoone as the <hi>Church</hi> came euidently by the fauour of <hi>Princes,</hi> to haue liberty to make lawes, and power to ſee them practiſed, it was neuer pretermitted to conſecrate the places. Before that, we find an ordinance by Pope <hi>Hyginus</hi> (he was within 150. after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the eighth <hi>Biſhop</hi> of that <hi>See</hi> after <hi>Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>) euen of particulars in the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crations. But after,<note place="margin">Athanaſ.</note> 
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie</hi> to <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> makes that prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation for all <hi>Chriſtians, That they neuer meet in any Church, till it bee conſecrated:</hi> And <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> leaſt hee ſhould be at any time vnprouided of ſuch a place, (as we read in the <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall</hi> ſtory) in all his warres, carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:24646:17"/>
with him a <hi>Tabernacle</hi> which was conſecrated: In <hi>Nature,</hi> in the <hi>Law,</hi> in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> in <hi>Precept,</hi> in <hi>Practiſe,</hi> theſe Conſecrations are eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſus.</note>This they did. But to what vſe did they conſecrate them? not to one vſe only; and therfore it is a friuolous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, whether <hi>Churches</hi> be for <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,</hi> or for <hi>praying.</hi> But if <hi>Conſecration</hi> be a kind of <hi>Chriſtning</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> &amp; that at the <hi>Chriſtning</hi> it haue a name, wee know what name <hi>God</hi> hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted for his Houſe, <hi>Domus mea, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus orationis vocabitur. My Houſe ſhall bee called the Houſe of Prayer.</hi> And how impudent and inexcuſable a falſhood is that in <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> That the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Caluiniſtes</hi> doe admit <hi>Churches</hi> for <hi>Sermons</hi> and <hi>Sacraments, Sed reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt quod fiant ad orandum,</hi> They diſlike that they ſhould be for <hi>Prayer:</hi> when as <hi>Caluin</hi> himſelfe, (who may ſeeme to bee more ſubiect to this reprehenſion then <hi>Luther</hi>) (for there is no ſuch <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:24646:17"/>
in the <hi>Caluiniſts Churches,</hi> as in the <hi>Lutheran</hi>) yet in that very place which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> cites, ſayes <hi>Conceptae preces in Eccleſia Deo gratae;</hi> and for ſinging in <hi>Churches,</hi> (which in that place of <hi>Caluin</hi> cannot be only meant of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> for it was of that manner of ſinging, which being formerly in vſe in the <hi>Eaſterne churches, S. Ambroſe,</hi> in his time, brought into the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Millan,</hi> and ſo it was deriud ouer the <hi>Weſtern churches,</hi> which was the modulation and ſinging of <hi>Verſicles</hi> and <hi>Antiphons</hi> and the like) this ſinging, ſayes <hi>Caluin,</hi> was in vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelues, <hi>Et ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſsimum &amp; ſaluberimum eſt inſtitutum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3.20. § 32.</note> 
               <hi>It was a most holy and moſt profitable Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</hi> Still conſider Conſecration to be a <hi>Chriſtning</hi> of the place; and though we find them often called <hi>Templa prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sacrificia,</hi> for our ſacrifices of praier, and of praiſe, &amp; of the merits of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and often called <hi>Eccleſiae ad conciones,</hi> Churches, in reſpect of congregations,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:24646:18"/>
for preaching, and often call'd <hi>Martyria,</hi> for preſeruing with reſpect, and honor the bodies of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and other <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> there buried, &amp; often, often, by other names, <hi>Dominica, Baſilica,</hi> and the like, yet the name that <hi>God</hi> gaue to his houſe, is not <hi>Concionatorium,</hi> nor <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarium,</hi> but <hi>Oratorium,</hi> the Houſe of Prayer. And therefore without preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the other functions too, (for as there is a <hi>vae</hi> vpon me, <hi>Si non Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zauero,</hi> If I preach not my ſelfe, ſo may that <hi>vae</hi> be multiplied vpon any, who would draw that holy ordinance of <hi>God</hi> into a diſ-eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or into a ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,) let vs neuer intermit that dutie, to preſent our ſelues to <hi>God</hi> in theſe places, though in theſe places there bee then, no other Seruice, but Common prayer. For then doth the Houſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to that name, which <hi>God</hi> hath giuen it, if it be a houſe of Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Modus.</note>Thus then were theſe places to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a double Dedication; a Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:24646:18"/>
which was a Donation from the <hi>Patron,</hi> a Dedication which was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration from the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> for to his perſon, and to that ranke in the <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> the moſt ancient Canons limited it; and to thoſe purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which wee haue ſpoken of; of which, Prayer is ſo farre from being none, as that there is none aboue it. A little ſhould be ſaid, (before wee ſhut vp this part) of the manner, the forme of Conſecrations. In which, in the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church,</hi> aſſoone as Conſecrations came into free vſe, they were full of <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> And many of thoſe <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> deriu'd from the <hi>Iewes:</hi> and not vnlawfull, for that. The <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which had their foundation in the prefiguration of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and were types of him, were vnlawfull after <hi>Christ</hi> was come; becauſe the vſe of them, then, implyed a deniall or a doubt of his being come. But thoſe <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> which, though the <hi>Iewes</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:24646:19"/>
vſed them, had their foundation in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> as bowing of the knee, lifting vp the eyes, and hands, and many, very many others, which either teſtified their deuotion that did them, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted their deuotion that ſawe them done, are not therefore excluded the <hi>Church,</hi> becauſe they were in vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Iewes.</hi> That <hi>Pope</hi> whom we named before, <hi>Hyginus,</hi> the eighth after <hi>Saint Peter,</hi> he inſtituted, <hi>Ne Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilica ſine Miſſa conſecretur. That no Church bee conſecrated without a Maſſe.</hi> If this muſt binde vs, to a <hi>Maſſe</hi> of the preſent <hi>Romane Church,</hi> it were hard; and yet not very hard truely; for they are eaſily had. But that word, <hi>Maſſe,</hi> is in <hi>Saint Ambroſe,</hi> in <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> in ſome very ancient <hi>Councels;</hi> and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intends nothing, to this purpoſe, but the Seruice, the Common Prayer of the <hi>Church,</hi> then in vſe, there. And when the Biſhop <hi>Panigarola</hi> ſayes in his Sermon vpon <hi>Whitſunday,</hi> that the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:24646:19"/>
               <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> found the bleſſed <hi>Virgin</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> at <hi>Maſſe,</hi> I preſume hee meanes no more, then that they were mett at ſuch publique Prayer, as at thoſe times they might make. Sure <hi>Pope Clemens,</hi> and <hi>Pope Hyginus</hi> meane the ſame thing, when one ſayes <hi>Miſſa conſecretur,</hi> and the other <hi>Diuinis Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus:</hi> One ſayes, <hi>Let the Conſecration bee with a Maſſe,</hi> the other, <hi>with Diuine Seruice;</hi> the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> the Diuine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice was then the <hi>Maſſe.</hi> In a word, a conſtant forme of Conſecrations, wee finde none that goes through our <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualls:</hi> the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> were ſtill more or leſſe, as they were more or leſſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious, or might bee ſubiect to ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize, or to be miſ-interpreted. And therefore I am not heere either to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, or ſo much as to remember, that which appertaines to the manner of theſe Conſecrations; onely in concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in that, which is the Soule of all, humble and heartie prayer, that <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:24646:20"/>
will heare his Seruants in this place, I ſhall not offend to ſay, that I am ſure my zeale is inferiour to none. And more I ſay not of the firſt Part, The Holy place; and but a little more, of the other; though at firſt it were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for an equall part, <hi>The Holy Perſon,</hi> That at the Feaſt of the Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>Ieſus walked in the Temple in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons Porch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </note>In this ſecond part, wee did not ſpread the words, nor ſhed our conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations vpon many particulars: the firſt was,<note place="margin">Jeſus in Templo.</note> that euen <hi>Ieſus</hi> himſelfe had recourſe to this <hi>Holy place.</hi> In the new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in <hi>Heauen,</hi> there is no <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 21.22</note> 
               <hi>I ſaw no Temple there</hi> ſayes <hi>Saint Iohn: for the Lord God Almightie, and the Lambe are the Temple of it.</hi> In Heauen, where there is no danger of falling, there is no need of aſſiſtance. Heere the <hi>Temple</hi> is called <hi>Gnazar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Paral. 4.9</note> that is <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xilium:</hi> A Helper: the ſtrongeſt that is, needs the helpe of the Church: And
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:24646:20"/>
it is called <hi>Sanctificium,</hi> by <hi>Saint Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.69.</note> a place that is not onely made ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Conſecration, but that makes others holy by GOD in it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, whoſe perſon and preſence might conſecrate the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> would yet make his often repayre to this <hi>Holy place;</hi> not that hee needed this ſubſidie of <hi>Locall holineſſe</hi> in himſelfe, but that his example might bring others who did neede it; and thoſe who did not; and, that euen his owne Preaching might haue the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite and the bleſsing of <hi>Gods</hi> Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in that place, hee ſayes of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Quotidie apud vos ſedebam do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens in Templo,</hi> and <hi>Semper docui in Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoga, &amp; in Templo;</hi> as in the <hi>Actes,</hi> the <hi>Angell</hi> that had deliuered the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> out of priſon, ſends them to <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes 5.</note> 
               <hi>Stantes in Templo loquimini ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi.</hi> The Apoſtles were ſent to preach, but to preach in the <hi>Temple,</hi> in the place appropriated and conſecrated for that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:24646:21"/>
holy vſe and employment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tempus.</note>He came to this place, and he came at thoſe times, which no immediate command of <hi>God,</hi> but the <hi>Church</hi> had inſtituted. <hi>Facta ſunt Encaenia,</hi> ſayes the Text; It was the Feaſt of the Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wee know what Dedication this was; That of <hi>Salomon</hi> was much greater; A Temple built where none was before; That of <hi>Eſdras</hi> at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne was much greater then this, An intire reedification of that demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Temple, where it was before. This was but a zealous reſtoring of an Altar in the <hi>Temple:</hi> which hauing beene prophaned by the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the <hi>Iewes</hi> themſelues threw downe, and erected a new, and dedicated that. <hi>Salomons</hi> Dedication is called a <hi>Feaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chr. 5.3.</note> a <hi>Holy day:</hi> by the very ſame name that the <hi>Feaſt</hi> of vnleauened bread, and the Feaſt of the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> is called ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Scripture,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 6.16.</note> which is <hi>Kag.</hi> The Dedication of <hi>Ezra</hi> is ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:24646:21"/>
to bee a ſolemne <hi>Feaſt</hi> too. But neither of theſe <hi>Feaſtes,</hi> though of farre greater Dedications, were <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſarie;</hi> neither commanded to be kept euery yeare; and yet this, which was ſo much leſſer then the others, the <hi>Church</hi> had put vnder that Obligation, to bee kept euery yeare; and <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe contemnes not, condemnes not, diſputes not the inſtitution of the <hi>Church.</hi> But as for matter of doctrine hee ſends euen his owne <hi>Diſciples,</hi> to them who ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chayre, ſo for matter of Ceremony, he brings euen his owne perſon, to the celebrating, to the authorizing, to the countenancing of the Inſtitutions of the <hi>Church,</hi> and reſts in that.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>it was Winter,</hi> ſayes the <hi>Text:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Etſi Hyeme</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> came <hi>et ſi Hyems,</hi> though it were Winter; ſo ſmall an inconuenience kept him not off. Beloued, it is not alway colder vpon <hi>Sunday,</hi> then vpon <hi>Satterday;</hi> nor at any time colder in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:24646:22"/>
the <hi>Chappell;</hi> then in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall.</hi> A thruſt keepes ſome off in <hi>Summer;</hi> and colde in <hi>Winter:</hi> and there are more of both theſe in other places, where for all that, they are more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be. Remember that <hi>Peter</hi> was warming himſelfe, and hee denyed <hi>Chriſt.</hi> They who loue a warme bed, let it bee a warme Studie, let it bee a warme profit, better then this place, they deny CHRIST in his Inſtitution. That therefore which CHRIST ſayes, <hi>Pray that your flight bee not in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.20.</note> 
               <hi>nor vpon the Sabboth;</hi> we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thus, Pray that vpon the <hi>Sabboth</hi> (I tolde you at firſt, what were <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths,</hi>) the Winter make you not flie, not abſtaine from this place. <hi>Put off thy ſhooes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 35.</note> ſayes <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> for the place is holy ground. When <hi>Gods</hi> ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance by his <hi>Church</hi> call you to this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place, put off thoſe ſhoes, all thoſe earthly reſpects, of <hi>eaſe</hi> or <hi>profit, Chriſt</hi> came, <hi>Et ſi Hyems.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:24646:22"/>But then, <hi>Quia Hyems,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quia Hyems</note> Becauſe it was Winter, Hee did walke in <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Porch,</hi> which was couered, not in <hi>Atrio,</hi> in that part of the <hi>Temple,</hi> which was open, and expos'd to the weather. We doe not ſay, that infirme and weak men, may not fauour themſelues, in a due care of their health, in theſe places. That he who is not able to raiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, muſt alwayes ſtand at the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> or bow the knee at the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> or ſtay ſome whole houres, altogether vncouered heere, if that increaſe infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of that kinde. And yet Courts of <hi>Princes,</hi> are ſtrange <hi>Betheſdaes;</hi> how quickly they recouer any man that is brought into that Poole? How much a little change of ayre does? and how well they can ſtand, and ſtand bare many houres, in the Priuy Chamber, that would melt and flowe out into Rhumes, and Catarrs, in a long <hi>Goſpell</hi> heere? But, <hi>Citra Scandalum,</hi> a man may fauour himſelfe in theſe places:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:24646:23"/>
but yet this excuſes not the irreuerent manner which hath ouertaken vs in all theſe places; That any <hi>Maſter</hi> may thinke himſelfe to haue the ſame li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie heere, as in his owne houſe, or that that <hi>Seruant,</hi> that neuer puts on his hat in his <hi>Maſters</hi> preſence all the weeke, on <hi>Sunday,</hi> when hee and his <hi>Maſter</hi> are in <hi>Gods</hi> preſence, ſhould haue his hat on perchance before his <hi>Masters. Chriſt</hi> ſhall make <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Seruant</hi> equall; but not yet; not heere; nor euer, equall to himſelfe, how euer they become equall to one another. <hi>Gods</hi> ſeruice is not a continuall <hi>Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> that a man muſt bee heere, and here in ſuch a poſture, and ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, though hee dye for it; but <hi>Gods</hi> Houſe is no <hi>Ordinary</hi> neither; where any man may pretend to doe what he will, and euery man may doe, what any man does. <hi>Christ</hi> ſlept in a ſtorme; I dare not make that generall; let all doe ſo. <hi>Chriſt</hi> fauoured himſelfe in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:24646:23"/>
the <hi>Church;</hi> I dare not make that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall neither: to make all places e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, or all perſons equall in any place.</p>
            <p>Tis time to end.<note place="margin">Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>Saint Baſill</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as acceptable as hee was to his Auditory, in his ſecond Sermon vpon the 14. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> takes knowledge that hee had preached an houre, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore broke off: I ſee it is a Compaſſe, that all Ages haue thought ſufficient. But as we haue contracted the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of great <hi>Temples,</hi> to this leſſer <hi>Chappell,</hi> ſo let vs contract the <hi>Chappell</hi> to our ſelues: <hi>Et facta ſint Encaenia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra,</hi> let this be the Feaſt of the Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſelues to <hi>God. Chriſt</hi> calls himſelfe a <hi>Temple, Soluite templum hoc:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 2.19.</note> Deſtroy this <hi>Temple.</hi> And <hi>Saint Paul</hi> calls vs ſo twice;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.16. &amp; 6.19.</note> 
               <hi>Know ye not that ye are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt? Facta ſint Encaenia noſtra: Encaenia</hi> ſignifies <hi>Reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uationem,</hi> a renewing:<note place="margin">Aug.</note> and <hi>Saint Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſayes that in his time, <hi>Si quis noua
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:24646:24"/>
tunica indueretur, Encaeniare diceretur. If any man put on a new garment, hee called it by that name, Encaenia ſua.</hi> Much more is it ſo, if wee renew in our ſelues the <hi>Image of God,</hi> and put off <hi>the Olde man,</hi> and put on the <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> This is truly <hi>Encaeniare,</hi> to dedicate, to renew our ſelues:<note place="margin">NaZian.</note> and ſo <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in a <hi>Sermon,</hi> or <hi>Oration,</hi> vpon the like occaſion as this, calls, <hi>Conuerſionem noſtram, Encaenia,</hi> our turning to <hi>God,</hi> in a true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or renewing, our dedication. Let mee charge your memories, but with this note more, That when <hi>God</hi> forbad <hi>Dauid</hi> the building of an Houſe, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was a man of blood,</hi> at that time <hi>Dauid</hi> had not embrued his hands in <hi>Vriahs</hi> blood; nor ſhed any blood, but lawfully in iuſt warres; yet euen that made him vncapable of this fauour to prouide <hi>God</hi> a houſe. Some callings are in their nature more obnoxious, and more expoſed to ſinne, then others are: accompanied with more tentations; &amp;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:24646:24"/>
ſo retard vs more in holy duties. And therefore as there are particular ſinnes that attend certaine <hi>places,</hi> certaine <hi>ages,</hi> certaine <hi>complexions,</hi> and certaine <hi>voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> let vs watch our ſelues in all thoſe, and remember that not only the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degrees of thoſe ſinns, but any thing that conduces therunto, prophanes the Conſecration, and Dedication of this <hi>Temple,</hi> our ſelues, to the ſeruice of <hi>God;</hi> it annihilates our repentance, and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates our former reconciliations to him. <hi>Almighty God worke in you a perfit dedication of your ſelues at this time; that ſo, receiuing it from hands dedicated to God, hee whoſe holy Office this is, may preſent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably this Houſe to God in your behalfes, and eſtabliſh an aſſurance to you, that God will be alwayes preſent with you and your Succeſsion in this place.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
